# Abhimanyu Sharan

+91-9611974574 | abhimanyu.sharan@gmail.com

### **Profile**

Friendly and engaging team player and mid-level professional with 2 years of experience as a mechanical design engineer. Specialized in thermo-fluids and computer aided design (3D CAD and 2D CAD). My areas of interest include industrial technology, engineering simulations, finite element method (FEA), computational fluid dynamics (CFD), turbomachinery, fluid mechanics, applied thermodynamics and more. Also interested in the software industry in web development and data science. Quick learner who can adapt to new practices quickly and possess good communication skills.

## **Experience**

#### CONSULTANT ERGONOMIST AND CORPORATE MANAGER | RECOUP | APRIL 2020 - PRESENT

- Current working in family business as an ergonomic consultant to various companies performing risk assessments of multiple client's workplace setups. Task also includes documentation of these assessments.
- · Also responsible for business development and fixing tie-ups with new reliable corporate clients, thereby gaining management experience.
- · Responsible for vendor partnerships and product management by collaboratively working with ergonomic and orthopedic products vendors.

#### MECHANICAL DESIGN ENGINEER | WEIR ENSCI | JULY 2018 - MARCH 2020

- My major work involved designing of scalable modular structures for different sizes of crushers and screens and building interfaces for easy selection of requirements. This was to suit a global requirement, and the structure would change accordingly to the dimensional and safety standards of the selected region and equipment size.
- Also worked on designing a user interface for automatic generation of a 3D assembled model and a general arrangement
  drawing of pump sets of different drive arrangements, as per requirements of Weir Minerals Europe. These helped
  improve productivity by a considerable amount since the order execution process was quickened and repetitive work
  was minimized.
- · Skills Acquired-
  - NX CAD Expressions based modelling, Teamcenter PDM, NX-Product Template Studio, NX Teamcenter Variant Configurator, Agile and Scrum Methodology on JIRA, Pump-motor-set assembly, scalable structure design, project engineering
- · Received a "Star Team Member Award" for completion of the primary crushing station module.
- · Extensive CAD (Computer Aided Design) practice on 3D modelling and assembly and 2D detailing on NX11.0 and NX8.5
- · Learnt about the different equipment used in mineral processing plant such as crushers, screens, conveyors, pumps and cyclones
- · Had executed billable projects as a member of the Engineering Automation and Plant Solutions teams
- · Have also understood how to read process flow diagrams and plan layouts.
- Attended numerous training courses in subjects including Engineering drawing and Standards, Lean Manufacturing, Value Engineering, Geometrical Dimensioning and Tolerancing, innovation, manufacturing processes, additive manufacturing, welding, and many more
- · Project on selection of centrifugal pump for slurry transportation and designing layout of a piping system within specified constraints

#### INTERN | TOYOTA INDUSTRIES ENGINE INDIA | JUNE-JULY 2016

- · Detailed observation of different manufacturing processes done in CNC Machines
- · Learnt the safety measures to be taken in the engine plant
- · Identified problems and suggested solutions in the line
- Project reported on measures to reduce coolant leakages in the production line- Suggested different engineering and administrative solutions to reduce coolant leakages in the production line by up to 25% per shift

#### **Education**

#### BACHELOR OF TECHNOLOGY | MECHANICAL ENGINEERING | 2014-2018 | PES UNIVERSITY - BANGALORE

- · CGPA: 9.07/10 and overall branch rank: 6
- · Bachelor's Degree with Thermo-fluids specialization and a minor degree in electronics and communication engineering.
- Specialization in the Thermo-Fluids Engineering domain by clearing course modules including turbomachinery, IC Engines, Jet propulsion, Power Plants, Basic and Applied Thermodynamics, Refrigeration, Basic and Computational Fluid Dynamics (CFD) and Heat Transfer
- Other courses in the design, manufacturing, aerospace, and automobile domains include Finite Element Method, Mechanical Vibrations, Design of Machine Elements, Material Science, Solid Mechanics and many more.
- · Hands on laboratory experience gained in various fields such as foundry and forging, machine shop, computer aided design, material testing, welding, engine test rig, heat transfer, microprocessors
- · Software Skills acquired: MATLAB, Solid Edge, ANSYS, CNC Programming
- · Other Skills acquired: Problem Solving, Arduino programming, Linear Algebra, Statistics and Numerical Estimation.
- · Projects-
  - Unified engineering project in building a ball shooting mechanism prototype using Arduino board, ultrasonic sensor, and DC motor
  - Final Year Project in heat exchanger analysis using FEA and optimization using different algorithms on MATLAB. Have a publication and a conference presentation for the same.
- · Also obtained a minor bachelor's degree which helped me gain some basic theoretical and practical knowledge in Instrumentations, Analog and Digital Electronics, VLSI Design and Communications Engineering.

#### **Skills & Abilities**

- · Computer Aided Design (Siemens NX8.5 and NX11 and Solid Edge)
- · Numerical computation using Computational Fluid Dynamics and Finite Element Analysis.
- Excellent communication skills (written and verbal communication), interpersonal skills and experienced in working in project teams
- · Passion in mathematics, problem solving and logical reasoning. Also skilled at playing Chess.
- Proficient in Python and MATLAB. Know basic object-oriented programming in C++, Java, Python and JavaScript along with data structures, algorithms, and modules. Have completed courses in Machine Learning, Data Science and Web development.
- · Technical skills in the mechanical, aerospace and software fields. Strong interest in R&D.
- · Creative, innovation, reliability, highly motivated, attention to detail, collaboration, leadership skills.
- · Complete willingness towards international travel.

#### **Achievements**

- · Rank holder medal for obtaining 6th rank in the mechanical branch during the undergraduate program.
- · Presented a paper at an international conference held at Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore in 2018.
- · Star team member award during my employment with Weir EnSci.
- · Merit scholarship awards and distinction cash awards during all my semesters.

#### Contact

- · Mobile number: +91-9611974574
- · Email ID: abhimanyu.sharan@gmail.com
- · LinkedIn Profile: https://www.linkedin.com/in/abhimanyu-sharan/
- · Personal Website: <a href="https://abhimanyusharan.github.io/">https://abhimanyusharan.github.io/</a>
- · Based in Bangalore, India but willing to relocate worldwide
- · Place of Birth: Mansfield, United Kingdom
- · Citizenship and Passport: Indian
- · Based in Bangalore, India but willing to relocate worldwide